I'd like to talk about my dad.
أود أن أتحدث عن والدي.
My dad has Alzheimer's disease.
والدي مصاب بمرض الزهايمر.
He started showing the symptoms about 12 years ago,
بدأت تظهر عليه أعراض المرض قبل 12 عاماً،
and he was officially diagnosed in 2005.
و تم تشخيص المرض بشكل رسمي سنة 2005.
Now he's really pretty sick. He needs help eating,
هو الآن مريض جداً. يحتاج إلى مساعدة عندما يأكل،
he needs help getting dressed, he doesn't really know where he is
و يحتاج مساعدة عندما يلبس، و لا يعلم بالضبط أين هو
or when it is, and it's been really, really hard.
أو متى، وهو أمر صعب للغاية.
My dad was my hero and my mentor for most of my life,
كان والدي هو بطلي ومعلمي طوال معظم حياتي،
and I've spent the last decade watching him disappear.
قضيت العشر سنوات الماضية وأنا أراه يختفي أمامي.
My dad's not alone. There's about 35 million people globally living with some kind of dementia,
والدي ليس الوحيد، لكن هناك نحو 35 مليون شخص في العالم مصابون بنوع من الخرف،
and by 2030 they're expecting that to double to 70 million.
و بحلول العام 2030 من المتوقع أن يتضاعف هذا العدد إلى 70 مليونا.
That's a lot of people.
ذلك عدد كبير من الناس.
Dementia scares us. The confused faces and shaky hands of people who have dementia,
الخرف يخيفنا. الوجوه المشوشة والأيادي المرتعشة للأشخاص المصابين بالخرف،
the big numbers of people who get it, they frighten us.
الأعداد الكبيرة للمصابين بالمرض تخيفنا.
And because of that fear, we tend to do one of two things:
ونتيجة لذلك الخوف نميل للقيام بأحد شيئين:
We go into denial: "It's not me, it has nothing to do with me, it's never going to happen to me."
نعمل على الإنكار: "لست أنا، هذا الأمر لا يخصني و لن يحدث لي إطلاقاً."
Or, we decide that we're going to prevent dementia,
أو نقرر أن نمنع الخرف من الحدوث،
and it will never happen to us because we're going to do everything right and it won't come and get us.
ولن يحصل ذلك لنا على الإطلاق وسنقوم بكل شيء كما يجب ولن يأتي خلفنا.
I'm looking for a third way: I'm preparing to get Alzheimer's disease.
أنا أبحث عن طريقة ثالثة: أنا أستعد لأصاب بمرض الزهايمر.
Prevention is good, and I'm doing the things that you can do to prevent Alzheimer's.
الوقاية أمر جيد، وأنا أقوم بالأمور التي يمكن القيام بها للوقاية من مرض الزهايمر.
I'm eating right, I'm exercising every day, I'm keeping my mind active,
أنا آكل بشكل صحي وأمارس الرياضة يوميا وأبقي دماغي فعالا،
that's what the research says you should do.
وهذا ما تقول الأبحاث أنه علي القيام به.
But the research also shows that there's nothing that will 100 percent protect you.
لكن الأبحاث تظهر كذلك أنه ليس هناك أي شيء سيحميك بنسبة 100 في المئة.
If the monster wants you, the monster's gonna get you.
إن كان الوحش يريدك فإنه سيصل إليك.
That's what happened with my dad.
ذلك ما حصل مع والدي.
My dad was a bilingual college professor. His hobbies were chess, bridge and writing op-eds.
والدي كان أستاذا جامعيا ثنائي اللغة. هواياته كانت الشطرنج والبريدج وكتابة مقالات الرأي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
He got dementia anyway.
وقد أصيب بالخرف على كل حال.
If the monster wants you, the monster's gonna get you.
إن كان الوحش يريدك فإنه سيصل إليك.
Especially if you're me, 'cause Alzheimer's tends to run in families.
وبالخصوص إن كنت أنا، لأن الزهايمر يميل إلى الاستمرار في العائلات
So I'm preparing to get Alzheimer's disease.
وبالتالي فإنني أستعد لأن أصاب بمرض الزهايمر.
Based on what I've learned from taking care of my father,
بالاعتماد على ما تعلمته من رعاية والدي،
and researching what it's like to live with dementia, I'm focusing on three things in my preparation:
ومن خلال البحث عما يعنيه أن تعيش بالخرف، أركز على ثلاثة أمور في تحضيري:
I'm changing what I do for fun, I'm working to build my physical strength,
أغير ما أقوم به من أجل الاستمتاع وأعمل على بناء قوتي البدنية
and -- this is the hard one -- I'm trying to become a better person.
و -- وذلك أصعب شيء -- أحاول أن أصير شخصا أفضل.
Let's start with the hobbies. When you get dementia, it gets harder and harder to enjoy yourself.
دعونا نبدأ بالهوايات. حين تصاب بالخرف، يصبح من الصعب أكثر فأكثر أن تستمتع بوقتك.
You can't sit and have long talks with your old friends, because you don't know who they are.
لا يمكنك الجلوس والحديث طويلا مع أصدقائك القدامى، لأنك لا تعرف من هم.
It's confusing to watch television, and often very frightening.
من المربك أن تشاهد التلفاز وأحيانا من المخيف جدا.
And reading is just about impossible.
والقراءة مستحيلة تقريبا.
When you care for someone with dementia, and you get training,
إن كنت تقوم برعاية أحد مصاب بالخرف، وحصلت على تدريب،
they train you to engage them in activities that are familiar, hands-on, open-ended.
يدربونك على إشراكهم في أنشطة مألوفة وعملية ومفتوحة.
With my dad, that turned out to be letting him fill out forms.
مع والدي فإن ذلك كان أن أدعه يقوم بتعبئة الاستمارات.
He was a college professor at a state school; he knows what paperwork looks like.
لقد كان أستاذا جامعيا في جامعة الولاية؛ فهو يعرف كيف يبدو العمل الورقي.
He'll sign his name on every line, he'll check all the boxes,
يقوم بتوقيع اسمه على كل سطر، ويضع علامات على كل الصناديق،
he'll put numbers in where he thinks there should be numbers.
ويضع أرقاما حيث يظن أنه يجب أن توضع أرقام.
But it got me thinking, what would my caregivers do with me?
لكن الأمر جعلني أفكر، فيم سيقوم به مقدمو الرعاية بالنسبة لي؟
I'm my father's daughter. I read, I write, I think about global health a lot.
أنا ابنة والدي. أقرأ وأكتب وأفكر كثيرا في الصحة العالمية.
Would they give me academic journals so I could scribble in the margins?
هل سيعطونني الدوريات الأكاديمية حتى أستطيع الخربشة في الهوامش؟
Would they give me charts and graphs that I could color?
هل سيعطونني مخططات ورسومات يمكنني تلوينها؟
So I've been trying to learn to do things that are hands-on.
وبالتالي فإنني كنت أحاول تعلم القيام بأمور عملية.
I've always liked to draw, so I'm doing it more even though I'm really very bad at it.
لطالما أحببت الرسم، وبالتالي فأنا أقوم به أكثر على الرغم من أنني لست جيدة فيه.
I am learning some basic origami. I can make a really great box.
أنا أتعلم بعض أساسيات الأوريغامي. أستطيع صناعة صندوق رائع.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And I'm teaching myself to knit, which so far I can knit a blob.
وأنا أعلم نفسي الحياكة، وأستطيع لحد الآن أن أنسج قطعة صغيرة.
But, you know, it doesn't matter if I'm actually good at it. What matters is that my hands know how to do it.
لكن، تعرفون أنه لا يهم إن كنت أجيدها. ما يهم هو أن تعرف يداي كيفية القيام بها.
Because the more things that are familiar, the more things my hands know how to do,
لكن بقدر ما هي الأمور مألوفة وبقدر الأمور التي تستطيع يداي القيام بها،
the more things that I can be happy and busy doing when my brain's not running the show anymore.
بقدر الأمور التي يمكنها أن تجعلني سعيدة ومشغولة، حين يكون يتوقف دماغي عن القيادة.
They say that people who are engaged in activities are happier,
يقولون أن الناس الذين يشاركون في الأنشطة يكونون أكثر سعادة،
easier for their caregivers to look after, and it may even slow the progress of the disease.
ومن السهل على مقدمي الرعاية العناية بهم، وقد يساهم ذلك حتى في إبطاء تقدم المرض.
That all seems like win to me.
بدا كل ذلك بالنسبة لي وكأنه كسب.
I want to be as happy as I can for as long as I can.
أريد أن أكون سعيدا بقدر ما أستطيع لأطول وقت ممكن.
A lot of people don't know that Alzheimer's actually has physical symptoms,
الكثير من الناس لا يعرفون أن مرض الزهايمر لديه بالفعل أعراض جسمانية،
as well as cognitive symptoms. You lose your sense of balance,
فضلا عن الأعراض الإدراكية. تفقد إحساسك بالتوازن،
you get muscle tremors, and that tends to lead people to being less and less mobile.
تصاب بارتعاشات عضلية، وذلك يميل إلى جعل الناس أقل حركية بكثير.
They get scared to walk around. They get scared to move.
يخافون من المشي. يخافون من الحركة.
So I'm doing activities that will build my sense of balance.
وبالتالي فأنا أمارس أنشطة لبناء حسي الخاص بالتوازن.
I'm doing yoga and tai chi to improve my balance, so that when I start to lose it,
أقوم باليوغا والتاي تشي لتحسين توازني، بحيث أنه حين أبدأ في فقدان عقلي،
I'll still be able to be mobile.
أكون كذلك قادرا على الحركة.
I'm doing weight-bearing exercise, so that I have the muscle strength
أقوم بتمارين رفع الأثقال، حتى تكون لدي قوة عضلية
so that when I start to wither, I have more time that I can still move around.
بحيث أنه حين أبدأ في الذبول، يكون لدي المزيد من الوقت للتحرك.
Finally, the third thing. I'm trying to become a better person.
وأخيرا، الأمر الثالث. أستطيع أن أكون شخصا أفضل.
My dad was kind and loving before he had Alzheimer's, and he's kind and loving now.
والدي كان طيبا ومحبا قبل إصابته بالزهايمر وهو طيب ومحب الآن.
I've seen him lose his intellect, his sense of humor, his language skills,
شاهدته يفقد فكره وحس دعابته ومهارته اللغوية،
but I've also seen this: He loves me, he loves my sons,
لكنني كذلك رأيت هذا: يحبني ويحب أبنائي،
he loves my brother and my mom and his caregivers.
ويحب أخي وأمي والقائمين على رعايته.
And that love makes us want to be around him, even now.
وذلك يجعلني أرغب في التواجد حوله، الآن حتى.
even when it's so hard.
حتى إن كان ذلك صعبا جدا.
When you take away everything that he ever learned in this world,
إن قمتم بأخذ كل شيء قد تعلمه من أي وقت مضى في هذا العالم،
his naked heart still shines.
لا يزال قلبه الشفّاف يسطع.
I was never as kind as my dad, and I was never as loving.
لم أكن قط بقدر طيبوبة والدي ولم أكن قط بقدر حبه.
And what I need now is to learn to be like that.
وما أحتاجه الآن هو تعلم أن أكون كذلك.
I need a heart so pure that if it's stripped bare by dementia, it will survive.
أحتاج إلى قلب غاية في النقاء، بحيث أنه إن جرده الخرف من كل شيء سيبقى على قيد الحياة.
I don't want to get Alzheimer's disease.
لا أريد أن أصاب بمرض الزهايمر.
What I want is a cure in the next 20 years, soon enough to protect me.
ما أريده هو علاج في العشرين سنة المقبلة، قريبا بما يكفي لحمايتي.
But if it comes for me, I'm going to be ready.
لكن إن تعلق الأمر بي، سأكون مستعدة.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)